Hi and welcome to Business Central
Launch Event 2024 Wave 2.
And this video is about what's new in AL
Go for GitHub. My name is Freddy
Christiansen. I'm the technical
evangelist and responsible for the AL Go
for GitHub product. Uh I'm also
responsible for Docker BC Container
Helper and other products that you might
be using.
Uh and I'm going to talk slightly about
those as well during this presentation.
So, let's have a look at what's new. I'm
going to talk about security
enhancement. Security is
important. Uh
if not the most important thing,
then
it's up there. I mean, if it's not
secure,
what's the purpose, right?
I'm going to talk about NuGet NuGet
support in AL Go for GitHub. Performance
tests has been in preview for some time.
I'm going to talk about samples, BC
Container Helper, and a little bit about
future investments that we're working on
and what we're going to to add to that
one.
First of all, security enhancements in
AL Go for GitHub.
So,
a few things that we did in order to
enhance security not only for our own
repository, but also for the customers
and partners using AL Go for GitHub
is
to always reference GitHub actions using
a commit
uh sha really, right?
Um and this this is for all non-AL Go
actions.
It's more secure than using a tag or a
branch. Uh
the
Dependabot can update this for us when
there's new versions in that. And we
will be running a full test suite on AL
Go for GitHub whenever there's a change
in
in a new version of these GitHub
actions. I'm going to show you briefly
what what this entails. If we look at
the one of the workflows that are
included in AL Go for GitHub, the CICD
YAML file, typically you wouldn't have
to to look into this one. Then, if we
are using an action like the checkout
action,
this is now no longer
actions/checkout@v4.1
or anything like that. This is the
actual SHA
of the action we're using. Now, you
might see that
when we're using an AL Go for GitHub
action, we are still using version 5.3.
The reason for that really is that this
gives us the ability to to hotfix these
actions, and we are in 100% control over
the AL Go actions. But, whenever we use
actions that are not in 100% control of
us, we will be using the SHA, meaning
that no change to the checkout action
will ever harm any of our users or
customers or partners.
Um, if we are using the preview version
of AL Go for GitHub, we are actually
doing exactly the same. Now,
that was wrong. We'll just go to the
um
the GitHub workflow for CICD here,
and looking at the preview version, also
the Microsoft AL Go action will be to a
specific SHA, meaning that when we
release another preview version of AL Go
for GitHub,
you will have to run update AL Go system
files in order to get the advantage of
that. We will always use the version
that you're running on to minimize
disruption really of people using AL Go
for GitHub.
Another thing we did, we added
pre-commit to ensure consistency of
files. That's uh markdown files and
other files that are checked using
pre-commit to ensure that uh general
file housekeeping really is in order.
And then last but not least,
federated credentials and managed
identities.
Um
No more secrets.
We basically have removed the the the
most of the reasons for having secrets
in AL for GitHub.
And I'm going to talk a little about how
that actually works.
If we look in the bad old days, not the
good old days, the bad old days, like if
we had something where we had a
repository maybe on GitHub maybe GitHub
didn't exist in the bad old days, but
anyway,
if you had a repository and you wanted
to
authenticate to some resources that
could be a key vault, some resources or
Business Central, that be it.
You read you needed like secrets for
username and a password and these
username and password
really be used in order to authenticate
to whatever resources you were trying to
authenticate to. The problem with this
is that
if these secrets were exposed, then
everything was exposed, right? Like your
life was exposed if you used your own
username and password. Now, there were
other ways of of of doing this and you
could create a specific user only for
this and
but in reality, a lot of people used
this as a real-time user and and this is
obviously
insecure. There are various
variations of this where you use
salted hashes hashes and instead of the
password to increase security and
actually our own
NAV / Business Central
web service key also was an example of
these things and it increases security
but but not by much. Like you will still
have one user that is exposed if
the secrets are ever exposed.
Then OAuth came, OAuth to the rescue.
Now, GitHub repository
uh the same repository, the same
resources that we want to authenticate
to. What you needed now was an intra-app
registration. And that intra-app
registration would really be like the
the the user that would need
access to something. Now, the intra-app
is not a real user. It's just a
registration of
um like a a proxy of an app that needed
to access these resources. And for that,
you'd need a tenant ID in which the
intra-app is, a client ID, and a client
secret.
It isn't much more uh secure than
username password because
if the client ID and the client secret
and the tenant ID was exposed, then you
actually might um
might be able to yeah, to access the
resources anyway. The way it works is
that you have an authentication service.
You you send your client ID, client
secret to that one, and you get an
access token back. Now,
the access to there's also in the OAuth
protocol, there's a reply-to, so you can
only get the access token to these uh
specific
when you're running the the workflow in
specific areas, but still it is possible
to circumvent that in in different ways.
Now, having that access token, you now
get access to to the resources. And uh
if the access token is exposed, then you
would
the the the the villain would actually
get access to the resource for the
validity of the access token.
If the client ID and the client secret
are exposed, then you might be able to
get access to all resources accessible
by the intra-app registration.
The problem with that this approach is
really that a lot of people reused
intra-app registrations for a lot of
things. So, the intra-app registration
ended up having access to a lot of
things that it didn't actually need.
So,
um again, yes, more secure than the
username password, but but really also
something that attackers could benefit
from. Variations of this would be to
have a client secret
a certificate instead for client secret.
That increases security,
but but still
there's there's a problem here. Now,
you could of course here like rotate the
client secret every month or the the
certificate every month and that
definitely increases security
quite a bit in this one.
But really the way you want to do
security like this is to instead of that
use
federated credentials.
Now, federated credentials is where you
don't need any secrets at all.
The how it works is that you have these
resources and on the resources
you can define who
are allowed to access this.
Now, you have an authentication provider
like GitHub
an authentic- authentication service
like the OAuth service I talked about
earlier.
Um, and then GitHub has the ability to
ask the authentication provider, "Who am
I?"
And the authentication provider will
return with an ID token specifying
repository, branch, and event.
Now, you can compare this with uh, user
getting a driver's license, right? If I
have a driver's license, everybody will
be able to look at that driver's license
and say, "Okay, there's a picture here.
This is Freddy and this is his name.
This is his age." Stuff like that. The
authentication provider is the Danish
state for my driver's license because
I'm from Denmark.
And people will trust that, right? So,
if we can find an authorization provider
that can authorize or can can tell me
tell like the world who I am
uh, using this ID token, then that is
deemed secure.
On the resources, I can define which
repo branch event has access to that
resource
either through an enter app and with a
managed identity or directly on the
resource in the Azure portal.
With that ID token,
I still need a client ID and a tenant
ID, resource ID, and I'll call the
authentication service in order to get
an access token. And again, I'll have an
access token and be able to
access all of these resources. The
tenant ID and the client ID are not
really secrets.
Uh we'll still store them in the secrets
uh template because yeah,
that's just how it was. Um but
if the access token is exposed, then you
will have access to the resource it for
the validity of the access token, which
typically is an hour.
Um
that can be bad enough, but typically we
don't see access token being exposed per
se.
There are no secrets, there are no
certificates to rotate.
If somebody needs to
do this, that be they they would need to
create an ID token that
that tells the world that this guy, like
they forge your off of uh fortify
my passport or my driver's license or
whatever,
that would make them able to to to do
stuff like this.
Um so this is the most secure way. Let's
have a demo of how this actually looks.
And have a look at
my Bing Maps app source
program here or I'll actually have a
look at my
built bars, which is my
uh federated credential here. So my
my built bars here is a managed
identity. This managed identity is set
up with access to my key vault, and the
key vault has my certificate for signing
and stuff like that.
And in this managed identity, I've
specified on the federated credentials
that this BC samples Bing Maps dot app
source
uh the main branch only
uh has access to
uh get a
GitHub issue token to impersonate the
application.
So, having set that up as a managed
identity, I can set up
the assignments for
this Build Wise managed identity
within my Azure Key Vault to have access
to
be a certificate user, meaning it can
uh get the certificate, it can sign the
app, and it can read secrets. So, these
are the three roles that my managed
identity need to have in order for that
to then um
be used. And looking at the Business
Central or the Bing Maps dot app source
action here.
Looking at the latest, I actually don't
know if that's too far ago, 2 weeks ago
should be fine.
Looking that and looking in build.
We should be able to see under sign here
that it
queries the federated federated token
and connects using client ID and
federated token. And thus uh uses
federated credentials for this one.
Another thing that is new in AL Go for
GitHub is NuGet support. Now, NuGet
support is something that we've been
working on for a long time.
Um
and
in this release, we have
symbols for all app source apps
available on a public NuGet feed.
Uh
AL Go for GitHub supports
trusting NuGet feeds, so you can trust
either private NuGet feeds or public
NuGet feeds.
Uh if you're trusting a public NuGet
feed, you can register prefixes and
fingerprints to like ensure that you're
not getting packages that you don't
really trust.
And and normally you should not trust
nuget.org unless
uh you have you're trusting like
registered prefixes or fingerprints.
Deliver to GitHub packages has been as a
proof of concept prototype in AL Go for
quite some time
uh and and that still works as earlier.
The deliver to NuGet has changed the
implementation now. We're using the same
mechanism as GitHub packages.
Earlier, the NuGet implementation was
like collecting apps and dependencies
into one NuGet package.
Uh the
the agreed upon NuGet format for
for Business Central apps
does not include multiple
apps in one package. Instead,
every single app has one package and
then you have like the full list of
dependencies in NuGet packages as well.
Um I had a session TechDays with Kamil
where we talked about the format in in
detail, and I recommend that you look at
that if you want to see the details of
how these NuGet packages
should work. Now,
as future investments, we will also be
able to publish runtime packages to
NuGet, either private or public, so that
you can share your NuGet feed with other
partners or customers.
If it's public, obviously they'll be
able to see everything. If it's private,
you can select the partners that you
want to to um
to share your packages with.
And we're also working on having all
first-party apps, meaning all Microsoft
apps, available in NuGet packages as
well as the app source symbols.
Now, let's have a look at how this
actually works. So,
let's go back to my browser here and
have a look at our AppSource symbols
feed. Now,
there are many apps in AppSource and
this NuGet feed actually contains them
all. So,
I can scroll down for quite some while
and still be at A or
So, let me just sort by this and search
for Abakion
Legal
and take one of these apps. So, this is
an app by Abakion. It has two versions
24.0 and 24
.1.
I can go to this version and I can
download the the symbols if I want to.
If I download the symbols,
it will look like this. There'll be a
NuGet package and there'll be a new spec
and an app file.
Looking in the new spec file,
it will look like this. So,
maybe scroll in a little bit.
Zoom in a little bit and
you'll see an ID. That is the
the format of the ID is is publisher,
name, and app ID.
And there's the version of the app and
then title, authors, and description.
There are no dependencies in the symbols
file because the symbols really don't
need to resolve the entire dependency
tree. Only the full apps will have that
requirement.
So, for that we we will have when we
create the full app packages on NuGet,
we'll have the entire dependency tree as
well.
Let's have a look at how this actually
works if we look inside
Business Central. I have a small PTE
here. In that PTE, I did in my PTE
take a dependency on the app that we
just talked about, the Abakion Legal app
here.
And that's the app ID and the name and
the publisher is Abakion.
And if I try to build this without
having access to these things, I will
get an error like this. Now, scrolling
down
and finding this one, a package with
publisher Abakion and Abakion Legal DK
and a version compatible with 24.0 could
not be found in the package cache
folders. Now,
obviously, it needs to find the
dependencies from somewhere.
In the old days, or before this release,
the typical way of doing that would be
to use the install apps
functionality, meaning you'd have to get
a package from Abakion,
download that, and like check in all the
symbols or the runtime package inside
your repository, much like this
dependency here. We have the Abakion app
in a zip file there.
And then in AL Go settings, we'd specify
install apps and dependency/star.zip,
take all the files that are there and
install that.
Now, that is what we want to get away
from.
Instead of that, what we can do now is
to add a trusted NuGet server. Now,
if I change here,
this one, trusted NuGet feeds,
and the NuGet feed here is Dynamics SMB
blah blah blah blah blah, AppSource
symbols NuGet version 3.
Now,
you you will not need to know this URL
because
this URL
will be built into AL Go for GitHub. We
will by default trust all Microsoft
trusted NuGet feeds, this one and the
feeds that uh
that will have our first-party apps, the
Microsoft provided apps, on will
automatically be trusted. But if you
have a
partner or you
uh that that has a NuGet feed, then you
can trust that NuGet feed just by adding
a trusted NuGet feeds inside uh AL Go
for GitHub.
Now, looking at checks, we'll see that
now it actually builds. And if we look
at the build for this one,
we should be able to see that installing
app dependencies
will actually now
go and see missing app dependency. This
is the app ID for the Abakian app. It
looks for NuGet packages for that,
searches the NuGet feed, and finds the
package, downloads that, and builds the
package.
Um
looking at
a few other ways that you actually can
do. I talked about fingerprints and and
and and prefixes.
When you do like trusted NuGet feeds,
you can specify a public URL if that's
what you trust. You can specify URL and
an auth token secret. The auth token
secret should specify a secret that
gives you an access token to that URL.
Uh
this piece does not yet
uh support federated credentials.
And then you can also say I want to have
this URL with this registered prefix.
These patterns of packages
are supported. Or this URL and then a
fingerprint, meaning that only if the
package is signed with a certificate
with that fingerprint,
uh I will trust the package and download
it to my machine.
Let's have a look at the GitHub packages
and the NuGet packages. If we look at
one of the CI/CD workflows here,
we will see that this one actually
delivers to both GitHub packages and to
NuGet.
And if I go to code, we'll see that now
this is the old format of
GitHub packages. There's a small change
to the name, Freddy K Freddy W1, which
is the app name, and then the app ID
instead of AL Go and then the app ID.
So, if you're using GitHub packages
already,
you will see that the name actually
changes. We will still be able to find
it because we only use the app ID for
resolving and then the version number.
So, if we look at this package,
we'll see that some versions are here
like from
1.0.43 to 1.0.660.
And then we can look at the other
package and see that now from
60 and upwards
here. So, if we're looking at 1.0.70
from that app ID, we will find it here,
else we'll find it in the other
way.
And this is the NuGet feed that I added
a NuGet context to. So, we can see that
this 3 hours ago the common and the
licensing and the miscellaneous and the
W1 was actually published here in a new
version exactly like we saw in the
GitHub packages.
Enough with NuGet pack NuGet support.
Another
new thing in
the latest version of Algo for GitHub is
a performance test. We actually were
able to run performance test earlier as
well. We just did not have the UI to
show whether the performance test was
good or good or bad. You'd have to like
download the performance test results
and compare it manually with whatever
baseline you wanted to use there.
The latest version of Algo for GitHub,
you will now have the ability to run
performance test either in CI/CD or in
scheduled test runs.
Uh
very much based on the settings where
you want to run it.
You can set a baseline and then the test
results will be compared to that
baseline. You can see whether it
regresses with a certain number of
percentages and you can set some
thresholds on
whether you you will allow a the the the
the regression to to be 5% 10% 15%
before you issue an error or a warning.
Now, how does that look?
Um let's again
go and look at the demo here.
For BCBT test results, this is my
repository that has a performance test.
It has an app, a test, and a performance
test here built in. In the root of of
this project, I'll have a baseline and a
threshold.
Uh the baseline can really be like a
test result from a prior run. You can
just copy that, or you can manually
obviously modify it if you if you want
to do that. Uh but you can just copy the
result of a prior run to the baseline
and say, "This is my baseline."
You can also see that the BCBT
thresholds here will will state that
uh
if they regress with more than 15%, I
will give a warning. If the duration
recurs with that, if
uh it regresses with more than 30%, I'll
I'll issue an error.
Now, it's also counting the SQL
statements. And if the SQL statements
are
above 10% higher than before, I'll issue
a warning. And if the SQL statements are
more than 20% higher than before, I'll
fail the build.
Let's have a look at the latest build
here and see if
uh anything
here.
This one should actually be fine. If we
look at the various
things down here, we'll see that your
the duration is six, and the baseline
was
6.5.
Here, that regresses uh 16% in the
duration.
Um we should be able to also scroll to
the right, right? It's here.
Um
and then up, minus 13%
and so on and so forth. The SQL
statements
uh base and the SQL statements this time
is actually the same all the way along.
We can have a look at how it looks if we
have warnings. Then having a look at a
prior run here and we'll see that
here we'll actually have some that
requests uh
more 17% and the SQL statements are the
same.
The reason why we really count the SQL
statements is that
uh very frequently that is the primary
reason for things to to regress in
performance. If you've done some created
some code or whatever that accesses the
SQL Server database more than earlier,
then that is one of the primary reasons
for for regressions
uh in that.
Another thing that's not like entirely
new, but something that we've been been
working on for for quite some time is
the BC samples
uh GitHub tag.
Now,
it's not really
AL Go for GitHub only, but let's have a
look at the
uh the tag here now.
What I can do here is I can say
aka.ms/bcsamples.
And it will show me all repositories on
GitHub that has the tag
BC samples.
And right now, this is only Microsoft
repositories, but if you have a
sample repository that you would like
people to see, um
then you can also just give it a tag BC
samples and then this it will end up in
this list. The current number of
of repositories here are six and we'll
have like all the repositories that were
created to showcase the the Power
Platform integration to AL Go for
GitHub, the BC samples take order, the
BC samples onboarding,
and the warehouse helper. Oh, the
onboarding is actually not
a Power Platform one. The warehouse
helper and the coffee MR, they are all
with Power Platform. The onboarding one
is one that really showcases how
onboarding is easier done. And then we
have two of the samples with Bing Maps
as a PTE and Bing Maps as an AppSource.
And you can obviously navigate to any of
these three repositories and have a look
at
what it contains. Typically, if we have
a look at one of these like takes the
warehouse helper.
If you want to like have a look at this,
try it out, you can you can press the
fork button here, create a local fork of
that. You will get everything. You'll
get the entire AL Go for GitHub setup,
and you'll be able to actually build
this together with the Power Platform
app and the Business Central app and set
it up to automatically deploy to your
Power Platform environment and your
environment. So, you'll get something
that you can start developing from if
you think that this is a good starting
point for your app, feel free to fork
that and there's absolutely no copyright
on the code or on the
repository itself. So, feel free to to
use these samples, and feel free to go
into your GitHub repository really in
the about section here
and add a topic. It's not a tag, it's a
topic. Sorry about that. Add a topic
called BC samples and you'll be able to
be listed in the list of BC samples
there.
Now,
I also want to talk about container
helper.
Container helper is a PowerShell module
that most of you might be using or
probably are using.
Right now, 2.25 million downloads,
approximately 3,000 downloads every
single day. And why talk about Container
Helper
in this forum?
Because AL Go will move away from using
Container Helper.
What does that even mean? So, BC
Container Helper today is just a huge
pile of cool cool functionality, really,
that helps partners do a lot of things.
And it can help you like do CAL code to
AL code to transformation. It can help
you spin up containers with NAV 2015. It
can help you like do all kinds of
things.
What we decided was to leave it like
that. Like, BC Container Helper will not
like go away. It will not be removed
from GitHub or from PowerShell Gallery.
But for people who using it for old time
stuff, it will remain as is.
We will, however, take all DevOps
relevant features and implement that in
either other PowerShell module and in
GitHub Actions.
And then will AL Go for GitHub will stop
using BC Container Helper.
Um
If you're using a managed DevOps
solution, if you're using AL Go for
GitHub, you might not even notice this
change.
Um if you are using a self-made DevOps
solution,
you will have work to do.
The commands in a new PowerShell module
will not be compatible with the commands
from BC Container Helper.
Uh and at some point in time,
BC Container Helper will no longer be
supported and will stop working. Now,
it's not going to happen day one when we
go away from using BC Container Helper
in AL Go for GitHub.
But eventually, like, there'll be a
PowerShell 8 or there'll be a .NET 9 or
there'll be stuff happening where it's
going to become too hard to maintain BC
Container Helper. If you have projects
that are using old versions of NAV and
Business Central and they're running in
in pipelines and stuff like that. BC in
container album might be able to run
those projects for a long time in the
future because no new
uh
requirements really are added to those
things. If you're running like projects
that needs to go on AppSource or PTEs
that needs to be installed in
online environments, I urge you to go
and switch to a managed DevOps solution
um because there
these changes will be made for you.
They'll be handled for you. You'll
always be able to run like when there's
new version of Business Central,
there'll be a a new version of either
the Azure DevOps tasks and ALOps or the
GitHub actions in in AL Go for GitHub or
the DevOps or GitHub actions that are
used in in Cosmo Alpaca. These three are
the solutions that we currently
uh look at as managed DevOps solutions.
If you're not using a managed DevOps
solution, if you're using something
you've coded yourself, you will be
spending a lot of time maintaining and
uh
developing these pipelines yourself and
and that is we think you can use your
spend your time
wiser. We think you can spend your time
on actually providing customer value
instead of doing pipelines and
workflows.
Last but not least, let have a look at
uh some future investments that are what
are we looking at into the future in AL
Go?
The picture here is really I asked
ChatGPT to create an image that
resembles uh Back to the Future with AL
Go for GitHub and uh
and and this is what I got. I actually
think it's a nice photo. So uh it's not
really DeLorean, but um yeah. So future
investments.
What I say now, there's no timeline,
there's no promises. It might
I actually some of them I'm pretty sure
they'll be there, but I'm no timeline.
But let's see.
The page scripting tests, like uh
recently just a week ago,
the BC replay and NPM package was
actually released to the public.
And that means that we can in AL Go for
GitHub start also executing or running
the page scripting tests as part of our
pipelines. We are not ready with that
today, so I actually think AL Ops beat
us to it.
But, that's absolutely fine. We'll also
provide the ability to run page scripted
tests
directly in your CI/CD or in your test
current test next minor and test next
major
workflows.
We're working on
like there are partners who need more
than what comes out of the box in AL Go,
so we're working on
indirect tape templates and
customization capabilities, and we're
not really sure where to land this one.
Some
say that that that Git functionality is
sufficient. Some say that we need to be
able to customize by adding custom
scripts or custom steps and custom jobs.
We'll land this and create documentation
on how to use these things. So, that
we'll like clearly document how partners
can and how much they can customize and
still
still keep current with the latest
version of AL Go. We don't want people
to
to just like
take AL Go as is and then run out of a
out of a different line because it
actually makes them run something they
made themselves just with AL Go as a
starting point. And whenever we finish
the investments of
of of removing the need for BC container
helper, they'll be like stuck there with
an old version of AL Go for GitHub, and
we don't want that.
We also will add mechanisms to generate
and publish runtime packages to NuGet.
We've talked about this for quite some
time. Now we have the symbols of app
source apps. That was actually the first
step on this journey. With these
symbols,
we'll be able to
with the with the small addition to the
to the AL compiler.
They might the team might not think it's
small, but let's see. We hope that the
AL compiler will be able to generate a
runtime package just by having the
symbols of the dependencies. That means
that we could generate runtime packages
for any
app that only has app source
dependencies or local dependencies
without having to create a service tier
for every single version we need to
generate runtime packages off
and publish all apps or the entire
dependency tree of the apps.
We can we can do with the symbols. This
will
immensely help partners share runtime
packages privately or publicly
with each other.
We'll add some more documentation, more
how-to videos,
and an updated roadmap so that this will
make life easier for partners and
customers using AL Go for GitHub.
And again, we'll make AL Go for GitHub
independent of BC Container Helper over
the next 2 to 3 years.
That's it for this one. Thanks for
listening.